Guide to the Caleb Budlong Physician's Account Books, 1817-1843, 1915 and undated RL.10078
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Caleb Budlong physician's account books
1817-1843, 1915 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Budlong, Caleb
RL.10078
4 Linear Feet 86 items
Collection comprises 8 medical account journals maintained by Budlong between 1817 and 1839. In addition to treatments provided, most often tooth extractions and bleeding, the doctor noted examinations and prescriptions for pills, oils, powders, elixirs, bitters, ointments, and asthmatics, along with cathartic sugars and throat lozenges. Fees are recorded for each entry and payments and regular audits noted. The entries were irregular in regard to date. Included in the collection is an undated typescript list of more than 100 individuals treated in volume 1, indicating that Budlong served as the primary physician for the area during its early settlement. There are indexes for volumes 2 and 8; and these, along with 76 items laid-in to the volumes, including receipts, blotting sheets, lists, calculations, and other notes have been removed to a separate folder. One item laid in is receipt unrelated to the volumes for a payment dated 1915.
Biographical Note
Dr. Caleb Budlong was born in Rensselaer Co., N.Y., in 1791. He moved to Frankfort (Herkimer Co.), N.Y., in 1793 with his parents. In 1815, he became the town's first postmaster, and in 1817 he graduated from Fairfield Medical College. He then served as a physician in Frankfort until his death in 1865. He also served as a member of the Frankfurt legislature in 1824, became town supervisor in 1835, and was an organizing member of the Universalist Church of Franfurt and German Flats in 1838. Fairfield Medical College stressed the development of the United States Pharmacoepia as a standard for uniform medical techniques, as well as a code of ethics for physicians. Budlong's professors were national leaders in these movements, and his practice was likely influenced by their work.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises 8 medical account journals maintained by Budlong between 1817 and 1839. In addition to treatments provided, most often tooth extractions and bleeding, the doctor noted examinations and prescriptions for pills, oils, powders, elixirs, bitters, ointments, and asthmatics, along with cathartic sugars and throat lozenges. Fees are recorded for each entry and payments and regular audits noted. The entries were irregular in regard to date. Included in the collection is an undated typescript list of more than 100 individuals treated in volume 1, indicating that Budlong served as the primary physician for the area during its early settlement. There are indexes for volumes 2 and 8; and these, along with 76 items laid-in to the volumes, including receipts, blotting sheets, lists, calculations, and other notes have been removed to a separate folder. One item laid in is receipt unrelated to the volumes for a payment dated 1915. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Caleb Budlong physician's account books were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a Purchase in 2011
Physicians -- Records and correspondence -- New York; Physicians -- History -- 19th century -- New York; Physicians -- New York -- Herkimer County.; Physicians -- Records.; Medicine -- Practice -- New York.; Medical fees.; Ledgers (account books); Medicine -- History -- New York; Drugs -- History.; Medicine -- Practice -- Accounting; Account books; Herkimer County (N.Y.) -- History.; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University); Budlong, Caleb; Budlong, Caleb
- Caleb Budlong physician's account books, 1817-1843, 1915 and undated; 8 volumes and 1 folder
  - Physician's account book, 1818-1823, bulk 1818-1819; 198 pages (Volume 1)
  - Physician's account book, 1820-1830, bulk 1822-1824; 261 pages (Volume 2)
  - Physician's account book, 1824-1836, bulk 1829-1832; 387 pages (Volume 3)
  - Physician's account book, 1826-1831, bulk 1826-1828; 209 pages (Volume 4)
  - Town and county account book, 1827-1831, bulk 1827-1828; 37 pages (Volume 5)
  - Daybook, 1833-1838; 331 pages (Volume 6)
  - Ledger, 1833-1839, bulk 1833-1836; 238 pages (Volume 7)
  - Ledger, 1838-1843; 272 pages (Volume 8)
  - List of individuals in v.1 that hold accounts, undated; 3 pages (Folder 1)
  - Indexes, v.2 and v.8, 1820-1830, 1838-1843 (Folder 1)
  - Items laid-in to volumes, 1828-1843, 1915 and undated; 76 items (Folder 1)